{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In the majority opinion of this case, its author pre-empted a dissenting argument by claiming, “This is not a question of substituting the judgment of the court for that of the legislature.” The case West Coast Hotel v. Parrish marked the end of a period named for this court case, in which Oliver Wendell Holmes wrote a dissent claiming, “The Fourteenth Amendment does not enact Mr. Herbert Spencer's Social Statics.” For ten points, name this Supreme Court case arising from a state law capping the number of hours bakers could work.",
      "answer": [
        "Lochner v. New York or Joseph Lochner, Plaintiff in Error v. People of the State of New York",
        "Lochner Era"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Following the Battle of Worringen, this city was granted town rights by Duke Adolf VIII [[the Eighth]] of Berg. This city's Stadtschloss housed a vast art gallery of the Wittelsbach family, who ruled the Electoral Palatinate. This city's district of Reisholz was severely damaged in an Allied attempt to destroy German oil refining capabilities during World War Two. Experiencing a historical rivalry with Cologne, for ten points, what is this city, the capital of North Rhine-Westphalia?",
      "answer": [
        "Düsseldorf",
        "Dusseldorp"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This historian may have mistaken a species of marmot found in the modern Baltistan region for the \"Gold-digging Ants\" of Homeric legend. The 2nd century BCE work, Arthashastra, [[ar-thah-SHAH-strah]] proved this man's claim that slavery did not exist in one culture was likely invented. After signing a treaty of friendship and ceding the region of Kandahar, Seleucus I Nicator [[seh-LOO-kus \"the first\" nee-KAY-tor]] deployed this diplomat to Pataliputra at the court of Chandragupta Maurya. The writer of Indika was, for ten points, what Ancient Greek historian who wrote the first thorough western records of the Indian subcontinent?",
      "answer": "Megasthenes ]"
    },
    {
      "question": "The founder of this organization was the son of a Quaker Oats co-founder who also served as ambassador to Norway. R. Douglas Stuart, Jr. created this organization, which was supported by Burton Wheeler. A Dr. Seuss cartoon highlighting the words “foreign children” criticized this organization that opposed the Atlantic Charter. Members of this group included Sargent Shriver and a young Gerald Ford, and its most prominent spokesman was aviator Charles Lindbergh. For ten points, name this often antisemitic organization that promoted American non-interventionism in World War Two.",
      "answer": [
        "America First Committee",
        "America First Party",
        "Editor's Note: generously",
        "the inclusion of \"Party\" in the alternate answer despite it historically being a different, but similar, party that was disavowed by the \"Committee\" 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A 2015 documentary titled for this group features interviews with Rolf Lüders and Sergio de Castro. Members of this group helped resolve the Crisis of 1982 through the use of price bands. This group's ideas were called \"El Ladrillo,\" [[lah-DREE-yoh]], or \"The Brick.\" Miguel Kast, a member of this group, freed the peso's fixed exchange rate with the U.S. dollar. Key teachers of this group included Arnold Harberger and Milton Friedman. For ten points, name this group of Chilean free-market economists who advised Augusto Pinochet [[pee- noh-CHEH]] and were educated at the namesake Midwestern university.",
      "answer": "\"Chicago Boys\""
    },
    {
      "question": "Yuri Andropov armed this leftist's opposition, including the general Hudson Austin who formed a 6-day long military dictatorship. This politician's father, Rupert, died during \"Bloody Monday,\" a leftist demonstration against the United Labor party of his nation's first post-independence leader, Eric Gairy. This man and his wife, Jacqueline Creft, the sitting Minister of Education, died by firing squad in the capital of St. George's. Bernard Coard's seizure of power and execution of, for ten points, what leader of the New Jewel Movement prompted an invasion of Grenada by the Reagan administration?",
      "answer": "Maurice Bishop or Maurice Rupert Bishop"
    },
    {
      "question": "Michael Brodhead’s “A West, Nasty Job” focuses on this project, which was inspired by a recommendation by Orville Childs. Joint rights regarding this project were initially called for by a treaty, partly negotiated by Sir Henry Bulwer, but were eschewed after negotiations with Adolfo Diaz’s government and the signing of the Bryan-Chamorro Treaty. The Mosquito Coast was to serve as the endpoint of this project, opposed by Augusto Sandinho. For ten points, name this proposed \"Canal\" that aimed to establish a path through a lake in a Central American country.",
      "answer": [
        "Nicaragua Canal or Canal de Nicaragua",
        "Nicaraguan Canal and Development Project",
        "Nicaragua Grand Canal",
        "Grand Interoceanic Canal"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Following a census at the beginning of this decade, a man posited, \"American democracy was born of no theorist's dream\" but \"came out of the American forest.\" Frederick Jackson Turner put forward his \"Frontier Thesis\" during this decade, in which the Billion Dollar Congress\" was voted out of office. During this decade, the Sherman Silver Purchase Act authorized the U.S. government to buy large amounts of silver, causing an economic panic. For ten points, name this decade which included the rise of the Populist Party.",
      "answer": [
        "1890s",
        "the Gay Nineties",
        "the Naughty Nineties"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One holder of this position is listed as the leader of the fourth and final “great age” in a work analyzing societal progress after the medieval era. In a philosophical work, an example of a statement that both denotes and does not denote refers to the “present” holder of this position. That work by Bertrand Russell also asks if a holder of this position “is bald.” Voltaire wrote about the “age” of a holder of this position, whom many thinkers associated with enlightenment absolutism during his 72-year reign. For ten points, give this position held by Louis XIV [[the Fourteenth]].",
      "answer": [
        "King of France or Roi de France",
        "King of the French",
        "or Roi des Français"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The DQI is modeled on the work of this man, who lends his name to a three-volume work by Colen Campbell. “Utility,\" “beauty,” and “strength” are listed as three central qualities of certain entities in this author’s best-known work. Levers relying on torsion springs were central to the ballista designed by this weapons designer. During the Renaissance, Leon Alberti studied the work of this man, who described the construction of aqueducts. For ten points, name this author of De Architectura, a noted Roman engineer.",
      "answer": [
        "Vitruvius or Marcus Vitruvius Pollio",
        "Vitruvius Brittanicus",
        "Vitruvian 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Tony Palmer and Edmund Harjo [[HAR-joh]] were among these specific people who were recognized by a 2008 act, and a 2002 film directed by John Woo and starring Nicholas Cage focuses on these specific people. A recommendation to the Marine Corps regarding the uniqueness of the Na-Dene [[nah DEH-nay]] family may have prompted the hiring of these people, who used the term iron fish to describe submarines. Many Navajo worked as these people, who used simple substitution ciphers. For ten points, name this wartime occupation of bilingual indigenous people who communicated secretly.",
        "answer": [
          "Code Talkers",
          "any answer regarding specific tribes",
          "ethnic groups Code Talking such as \"Navajo Code Talker\"",
          "Code Talkers Recognition Act",
          "Windtalkers"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Among the tribes that made up the Code Talkers were what noted horsemen sometimes referred to as “Lords of the Plains\"? A Finnish historian argued in a 2008 book that their landholdings in modern Texas, Oklahoma, and New Mexico comprised an \"Empire.\"",
        "answer": [
          "Comanche or Nʉmʉnʉʉ",
          "Comancheria",
          "or Nʉmʉnʉʉ Sookobitʉ"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A poster widely circulated as part of this effort depicts a suited cartoon figure next to the words “the Children’s best friend.” Nearly one million cats and dogs were slaughtered in preparation for this effort, during which the slogan “Mend and Make Do” was widely used. Material for tarpaulin was reduced due to this effort, and unused margarine coupons were sometimes exchanged for clothing during it. Beginning in 1939 in anticipation of a “total war”, for ten points, what was this austerity effort in a country led by Winston Churchill?",
        "answer": [
          "British Rationing in World War Two",
          "Rationing in Great Britain",
          "United Kingdom",
          "England in place of Great Britain"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The British government encouraged its populace to “dig for” what concept, “gardens\" of which were developed to supplement rations with home-grown vegetables?",
        "answer": [
          "Victory",
          "“Dig for Victory”",
          "Victory Gardens"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Clarence Thomas once claimed that this text did not prefer a \"repressive cure\" for certain entities. Charles Beard argued that this text demonstrates one man’s belief that “the first and elemental concern of every government is economic.\" Those “united and actuated by some common impulse of passion” are referred to in this work, which was seen as an attack on both direct democracy and the formation of political parties. For ten points, name this essay which questions how to safeguard against factions, part of a larger work written by James Madison, John Jay, and Alexander Hamilton.",
        "answer": "Federalist Paper Number 10"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Every writer of the various Federalist Papers published under what pseudonym?",
        "answer": "Publius"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The penultimate ruler of this dynasty abdicated the throne to his infant son after a disastrous campaign in the Caucasus. This dynasty's founder wrote many poems under the name Khataʾi and was defeated at the Battle of Chaldiran. Another ruler from this dynasty, Tahmasp, signed the Peace of Amasya in 1555. This dynasty established the Twelver School of Shia Islam as the state religion for their empire. For ten points, name this Persian royal dynasty which ruled from 1501 to 1736 and formed a namesake gunpowder empire.",
        "answer": [
          "Safavid Dynasty",
          "Safavids",
          "Safavid Iran",
          "Safavid Persia",
          "Safavid Empire"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Under Abbas the Great, which city became the Safavid capital? This city's Safavid buildings include the Ali Qapu, the Shah Mosque, and the Naqsh-e Jahan Square.",
        "answer": "Isfahan or Esfahān"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One man claimed that, with this agreement, a “phase of benign despotism is over.” A group of MPs in the United Kingdom, who opposed John Major’s implementation of this treaty’s terms, were known as its namesake “rebels.” Debt and deficit are criteria stipulated by this treaty for the adoption of a certain currency. The Treaty of Lisbon superseded this treaty which was signed in 1992 by twelve members of the European Communities. For ten points, name this foundational treaty for the European Union.",
        "answer": [
          "Maastricht Treaty",
          "Treaty on European Union before “European Union” is mentioned",
          "Maastricht Rebels"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Signed in 1967, what treaty was signed that unified the executive functions of the European Economic Community, the European Coal and Steel Community, and Euratom treaties into one shared agreement?",
        "answer": [
          "Merger Treaty",
          "Treaty of Brussels 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An incident involving this nearly 400-year old company was streamlined by a middleman representing the Italian company Snamprogetti. Though it originally sold forged steel to customers in Finspang, this company started to manufacture cannons in the 1880s before its acquisition by the inventor of dynamite. Alfred Nobel once owned this company that made headlines in the 1980s for alleged kickbacks it gave to a prime minister of the Congress Party of India. For ten points, Rajiv Gandhi was embroiled in a scandal involving what Swedish arms manufacturer?",
        "answer": "AB Bofors"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Part of the Bofors Scandal involved the sale of what kind of large field artillery pieces to India? This weapon takes its name from the Czech word for \"crowd\" as they were once fired into crowds of infantry.",
        "answer": [
          "Howitzers",
          "Haubits FH77",
          "or Fälthaubits 77"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A list of 116 victims of this event was included in a “White Book” written by emigres in France. A couple weeks before this event, Franz von Papen gave a speech calling for a \"second revolution\" to students in Marburg. One victim of this event, Gustav von Kahr, had previously helped to put down the Beer Hall Putsch. Ernst Röhm was personally arrested during this event, alongside the SA, or \"Brownshirts.\" For ten points, name this mass purge ordered by Hitler.",
        "answer": [
          "Night of the Long Knives or Nacht der Langen Messer",
          "Operation Hummingbird",
          "or Unternehmen Kolibri",
          "Röhm Putsch before “Röhm” is mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What ideological branch of Nazism, which was crushed during the Night of the Long Knives, was named for two German brothers and advocated for an \"antisemitic economy,\" contrasting with Hitler's willingness to accept capitalists into his government?",
        "answer": [
          "Strasserism",
          "Gregor Strasser",
          "or Otto Strasser",
          "Strasser brothers 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One holder of this position introduced the Mind Your Own Business Act, and another holder of this position was staunch Vietnam War opponent Wayne Morse. The only woman to hold this position was Maurine Neuberger. In 2021, the senior holder of this position, who first took his seat from Bob Packwood, became chair of a certain Congressional Finance Committee. For ten points, name this Congressional position from a Pacific Northwest state which has been held by people including Mark Hatfield and Ron Wyden.",
        "answer": "United States Senator from Oregon"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Republican senator from Oregon was the Senate Minority Leader from 1933 to 1944 and ran for vice president in 1940 under the Wendell Wilkie ticket?",
        "answer": "Charles Linza McNary"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this musical, four characters sing about the power of a single weapon to change the world in \"The Gun Song.\" A character cakewalks up to a noose during his hanging in this musical to the tune of his own song \"I am going to the Lordy.\" Two characters in this musical shoot a bucket of chicken and share memories of Charles Manson. Historical figures like Emma Goldman and Giuseppe Zangara appear in this musical, in which the title characters open fire on the audience. For ten points, name this Stephen Sondheim musical about people who tried to kill presidents.",
        "answer": "Assassins"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Two female assassins, and Manson Family members, who attempted to kill Gerald Ford appear in Sondheim's musical. One of them is Squeaky Fromme, and the other is this woman who, in the musical, throws bullets at Ford while shouting \"Bang!\"",
        "answer": "Sara Jane Moore or Sara Jane Kahn"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's death sparked a ten year long interregnum and civil war which culminated at Battle of Çamurlu [[chah-MOOR-loo]], where one brother backed by Stefan Lazarević of Serbia defeated this ruler's sibling Musa Çelebi [[jeh-LEH-bee]]. Manuel II's ability to receive grain shipments allowed the Byzantine capital to withstand an attempted 1391 siege by this ruler. This man was supposedly placed in a golden cage and paraded around Anatolia following his loss at the Battle of Ankara. The nickname \"The Thunderbolt\" was bestowed upon, for ten points, which Ottoman sultan?",
        "answer": [
          "Bayezid I",
          "Bayezid the Thunderbolt",
          "or Yıldırım Bayezid"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Following the Battle of Ankara, which conqueror imprisoned Bayezid until his ransom?",
        "answer": "Tamerlane 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Prohibition Era",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Prohibition Era in the U.S., name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Bootlegger known as \"Scarface\" whose henchman perpetrated the St. Valentine's Day Massacre.",
          "answer": "Al Capone or Alphonse Gabriel Capone"
        },
        {
          "question": "General term for underground bars and clubs that served alcohol during the era.",
          "answer": [
            "Speakeasy",
            "\"Blind Pig\""
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Amendment which led to Prohibition being implemented nationwide.",
          "answer": "18th Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Act\" named for a Chairman of the House Judiciary Committee which enforced Prohibition.",
          "answer": "Volstead Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nickname for the Bureau of Prohibition team led by Eliot Ness.",
          "answer": "\"The Untouchables\""
        },
        {
          "question": "Resort city in Texas known as the \"Free State\" due to being an illicit alcohol and gambling hub run by the Maceos.",
          "answer": [
            "Galveston",
            "Galveston Island"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Jewish gang of bootleggers who committed the Milaflores Massacre during the Detroit Mob War.",
          "answer": "Purple Gang or Sugar House Gang"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Man in the Green Hat\" who sold liquor to congressmen and sold his story to the Washington Post in 1930.",
          "answer": "George Cassiday or George L. Cassiday Sr. 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Reign of Marcus Aurelius",
      "prompt": "Concerning Emperor Marcus Aurelius, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Work of Stoic philosophy he wrote while campaigning.",
          "answer": [
            "The Meditations of Marcus Aurelius",
            "Ta eis heuton",
            "Things to One's Self"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Number of \"Good Emperors\" of which he was one.",
          "answer": "Five Good Emperors"
        },
        {
          "question": "Son and successor of his, known for personally fighting in the Colosseum.",
          "answer": [
            "Commodus or Lucius Aelius Aurelius Commodus",
            "or Marcus Aurelius Commodus Antoninus"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Predecessor and uncle of his who built a namesake wall in Southern Scotland.",
          "answer": [
            "Antoninus Pius or Titus Aelius Hadrianus Antoninus Pius",
            "Antonine Wall"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Iranian power whose capital, Ctesiphon, was sacked by an army he sent.",
          "answer": [
            "Parthian Empire",
            "Arsacid Empire"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Bloody wars against a namesake Trans-Danubian tribe alongside the Quadi and Sarmatians.",
          "answer": [
            "Marcomannic Wars",
            "Bellum Germanicum et Sarmaticum"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Wife of his who may have encouraged General Avidius Cassius to make a bid for the throne in 175.",
          "answer": [
            "Faustina the Younger or Faustina Minor",
            "Annia Galeria Faustina the Younger",
            "Annia Galeria Faustina Augusta Minor"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Beloved Roman grammarian from Numidia who tutored him and Lucius Verus.",
          "answer": "Fronto or Marcus Cornelius Fronto 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Boshin War",
      "prompt": "Concerning the 19th century Boshin War, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "\"Restoration\" of Imperial power which prompted the war.",
          "answer": [
            "Meiji Restoration or Meiji Ishin",
            "Honorable Restoration",
            "or Goisshin"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City which was renamed to Tokyo shortly after its fall in the war.",
          "answer": "Edo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Northern Japanese island where the Ezo Republic was founded by pro-Shogunate forces.",
          "answer": "Hokkaido"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of American steamship sold to the Imperials due to a surplus after the U.S. Civil War.",
          "answer": [
            "Ironclads",
            "Kotetsu",
            "Azuma",
            "the CSS Stonewall"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Last Tokugawa shogun whom the daimyos hoped to restore to power.",
          "answer": [
            "Tokugawa Yoshinobu",
            "Keiki"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "revolt of disaffected samurai.",
          "answer": [
            "Satsuma Domain",
            "Satsuma Revolt"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "First major battle of the war, fought over control of Kyoto.",
          "answer": "Battle of Toba–Fushimi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Specific type of matchlock introduced by the Portuguese which was still in use during the war.",
          "answer": "Tanegashima"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An island, which was named for this person during the Arctic Ocean Hydrographic Expedition in 1913, was later renamed Maly Taymyr. A CIA agent, codenamed \"Sniper Lavinia,\" claimed in his later life to be this person. Two sailors, Andrei Derevenko and Klementy Nagorny, were hired (20 pts)",
        "as nannies to make sure this person didn’t injure themselves. After suffering from an internal hemorrhage, (10 pts)",
        "this person was treated by Grigori Rasputin. Plagued with hemophilia, for ten points, what royal was Empress Alexandra and Emperor Nicholas II’s only son?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Alexei Nikolaevich, Tsarevich of Russia or Alexei Romanov",
        "Alexei II"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An opinion from this case asks if one group is “to enjoy the high priviledge of acting thus eminently wrong.” William Cushing and John Blair wrote opinions in this case, which asked if a certain type of defendant “is amenable to the jurisdiction (20 pts)",
        "of the Supreme Court.” The question of sovereign immunity was central to this case, which dealt with whether a private citizen of one state could sue a (10 pts)",
        "different state in federal court. For ten points, name this suit, often considered the first significant case in Supreme Court history."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Chisholm v. Georgia",
        "Alexander Chisholm, Executors v. Georgia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Members of this kingdom wore a type of loincloth called the “Gundhate,” which is still worn by their descendants. Gerehu and Eti were a ruling couple of this kingdom, which was known for its blackwood and resin. A landscape depicting two date palms (20 pts)",
        "within this kingdom can be found on the walls of the Deir el-Bahri complex. That temple dedicated to Queen Hatshepsut features artwork inspired by an expedition to this kingdom that Flinders Petrie claimed was “a district at the (10 pts)",
        "south end of the Red Sea.” For ten points, name this East African empire that traded with Egypt."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Land of Punt",
        "Kingdom of Punt",
        "or Puntland",
        "Pwenet",
        "Ta Netjer",
        "or Land of God"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This singer's popularity in Utrecht led her to say, \"I thought I was the Beatles!\" During the Depression, this singer eschewed steady work to become a self-proclaimed “fish and bread singer.” A cover of this singer’s “Move On Up A Little Higher” (20 pts)",
        "was recorded by Marian Anderson. Invited to perform “The Star Spangled Banner” at the inaugural ball for John F. Kennedy, this Chicago native performed a rendition of Clara Ward’s “How I Got Over” in front of more than 250,000 people during the 1963 (10 pts)",
        "March on Washington. For ten points, name this prominent gospel singer and Civil Rights activist."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Mahalia ] Jackson",
        "Mahala Jackson 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One controversy surrounding this person involved two men, Grigory Landsberg and Leonid Mandelstam, being nominated for a Nobel Prize despite citing this man’s work in their research. This person publicly embarrassed Jawaharlal Nehru (20 pts)",
        "after the prime minister believed that a piece of copper under ultraviolet light was gold. This scientist’s student, K. S. Krishnan, was not nominated for the Nobel Prize despite being the co-author on most of his (10 pts)",
        "scientific papers. For ten points, what physicist of Indian descent names an “effect” explaining the scattering of light?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "C. V. Raman or Chandrasekhara Venkata Raman",
        "Raman Effect",
        "or Raman Scattering"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Jacob Le Maire was among the first Europeans to visit this country’s Traitor’s Island. An Englishman, named William Mariner, wrote an account of his time living in this country, which was often visited by whaling vessels like the Albatross. The film The Other Side of Heaven (20 pts)",
        "chronicles Mormon missionary efforts in this country. Former Bank of America employee Jesse Bogdonoff served as an advisor and court jester to a king of this country, Tāufaʻāhau (10 pts)",
        "Tupou IV [[toh-fah-AH-how TOO-poh the Fourth]]. For ten points, name this Polynesian country, a former British protectorate."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Kingdom of Tonga",
        "Puleʻanga Fakatuʻi ʻo Tonga"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Members of this organization, Rafael Ramos and Wenjian Liu, were killed in 2014 by a man who was outraged at the release of Daniel Pantaleo. The Knapp Commission was created to investigate this organization, several of whose members approached a man thought to have been selling (20 pts)",
        "cigarettes lacking tax stamps. That man, Eric Garner, was put into a chokehold by members of this organization whose highest-ranking women have included Juanita Holmes and (10 pts)",
        "Keechant Sewell. For ten points, name this law enforcement agency operating in boroughs including Manhattan."
      ],
      "answer": "City of New York Police Department or NYPD"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this city in 1962, a tank tragically ran over onlookers at a military parade in a covered-up incident. This city was the construction site of the pre-dreadnought battleship Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse. A 1630 treaty named for this city justified Gustavus Adolphus's occupation (20 pts)",
        "of its entire region. Winston Churchill noted that one boundary stretched from “Trieste in the Adriatic” (10 pts)",
        "to this Baltic city in his “Iron Curtain” Speech. Formerly the capital of the Duchy of Pomerania, for ten points, what is this seaport which was given to Poland by the Potsdam Agreement?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Szczecin or Stettin",
        "Treaty of Stettin 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Civilians opposed to this conflict created the \"Cadets of the Cross\" and killed 52 people in the village of Brenoux [[breh-NOO]]. A group of people under Elie Marion, who surrendered during this conflict, emigrated to London and were scorned as \"French Prophets.\" (20 pts)",
        "This revolt was led by Roland Laporte and Jean Cavalier, the latter of whom surrendered in the Cevennes [[seh-VEHN]] region. Following Louis XIV's [[the Fourteenth's]] revocation of the Edict of Nantes [[NAHNT]], (10 pts)",
        "this revolt's namesake group rebelled against continued persecution. For ten points, name this early 1700s Huguenot rebellion, named for a type of smock."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Camisard revolt or War of the Camisards",
        "Cévennes War until \"Cevennes\" is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One side in this war employed two former Russian Civil War generals to lead the general staff, while the other side's Minister of War, Hans Kundt, mass purchased tanks which proved ineffective in this war’s namesake region. A type of unique hand grenade known as the carumbe'i, (20 pts)",
        "which is the Guarani word for \"Little Turtle,\" was developed for this war by an army led by Eusebio Ayala. A peace conference in (10 pts)",
        "Buenos Aires ceded much of this war's namesake region to Paraguay. Bolivia and Paraguay vied for control of the namesake semi-arid lowlands in, for ten points, which 1930s conflict?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Gran Chaco War or Guerra del Chaco",
        "or Cháko Ñorairõ 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    }
  ]
}